TheChaosLegion
I want to shine on you, and always like that dazzling sun.
I will defend you from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
If only our hearts could connect, I could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time, and I know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day, I'll be there for you.
I hope I can watch over you like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
I bring news!
（無人の体(てい)）伝令にございます
（聖導師(せいどうし)）ご苦労であった
Well done.
（帝(みかど)）吉報であろうな
Good news, I trust?
Yes.
（聖導師）はい
チャグム皇太子殿下は
あしき魔物を退け―
His Highness Prince Chagum
has driven off the evil demons...
...rendered assistance in
the birth of the water spirit...
水の精霊の誕生に
ご尽力あそばし―
...and is returning to the
palace at this very moment.
ただいま 帰宮の途にあるとの
ことにございます
（帝）大儀であった
He has done well...
これより かん口令を解き―
I shall immediately lift the order of
silence and have the entire palace...
宮を上げ
式典の準備に当たらせます
...begin preparations
for a ceremony.
（帝）天の加護を受け
建国の道を開いた―
Let it be known far and wide.
He is the founding father Torugaru
reborn, who, by the grace of heaven...
聖祖トルガルの
生まれ変わりとして―
内外に伝え聞かせよ
...paved the way for the
creation of our country.
Yes, Sire.
Episode 26
Departure
（チャグム）ねえ バルサ？
Say, Balsa...
ナージは もう
卵を海まで運んだかな？
Do you think the nahji has carried
the egg all the way to the sea by now?
いつごろ
水の精霊になるんだろう
I wonder when it will
become a water spirit?
I'm not sure.
（バルサ）さあねえ
But if it doesn't start
belching out some clouds soon...
でも 早いとこ
雲を吐いてくれなきゃ―
...the harvest this fall
is going to be poor.
今年の秋は大凶作だよ
You're right.
（チャグム）そうだね
Come to think of it, Teacher, what
do you suppose Rarunga normally eat?
（タンダ）そういや 師匠―
ラルンガは ふだんは
何を食っていたんでしょうね
I doubt that they go 100 years
without eating anything.
まさか 100年の間―
何も食べていないってことは
ないですよね
（トロガイ）そんなことはあるまい
Of course not. Even those
monsters are living things.
あれだって 生き物には違いない
いつもは別の物を食っていて―
I expect that they eat other
creatures the rest of the time...
...and the Nyunga Ro Chaga are
a treat they only get once a century.
ニュンガ･ロ･チャガは100年に一度
食えるごちそうなんだろうよ
Now I see. Even though
they're called egg-eaters...
（タンダ）なるほど
確かに 卵食いと呼ばれていても―
実際には
卵は食えないわけですからね
...they can't actually eat the eggs.
俺以外にも卵を
産みつけられていた者がいたのか？
Was there anyone besides me
that was implanted with an egg?
ん？ ああ 若い熊がな
ラルンガに食われるところを見たよ
Actually, there was a bear cub.
We saw it get eaten by a Rarunga.
Oh.
そうか…
（暗殺兵）いかがいたします？
What would you like us to do, sir?
皇子が短槍(たんそう)使いのそばを
離れる機会は そうありません
The prince seldom leaves
the spear-wielder's side.
Forgive me, female bodyguard.
（シュガ）許されよ 女用心棒
Wait!
（モン）待たれよ
Master Shuga, even if you were
so ordered by the mikado...
（ジン）シュガ様―
いかな帝の命令とはいえ
もはや その必要はありますまい
...surely it is no longer necessary.
None of us wish to cause
His Highness more grief.
誰も皇子の悲しむ顔は
見たくはありません
（モン）その思い
誰よりも あなた様が一番強いはず
You should feel that desire
more keenly than anyone.
Yes, you are right. I was
about to do the wrong thing.
（シュガ）そうだな
道を間違えるところであった
帝には私から話してみる
I shall discuss this with the mikado.
Mon, Jin, thank you.
You have my gratitude.
モン ジン ありがとう 感謝する
チャグム みこしに乗ってやれよ
みんな肩身が狭そうだぞ
Chagum, go ride in the palanquin.
They look embarrassed.
I can't do that.
ダメだよ
タンダが ケガをしているのに―
It wouldn't feel right to ride in the
palanquin when you're hurt, Tanda.
俺だけ みこしに乗るなんて
おかしいよ
I appreciate the sentiment, but...
気持ちは うれしいけど
（バルサ）いいじゃないか
Oh, let him have his way.
Chagum says he doesn't mind.
チャグムが
“いい”って言ってるんだから
Right. And besides,
we're almost at Kosenkyo.
（チャグム）そうだよ
それに もうすぐ光扇京(こうせんきょう)だし
Balsa...
バルサ…
まずは おっかさんに
元気な姿を見せてやったらどうだい？
Why don't you start off by letting
your mother see that you're safe?
I have made arrangements
for you within the palace as well.
（シュガ）そなたたちにも
宮中(きゅうちゅう)に部屋を取らせてある
沙汰があるまで くつろいでくれ
Please relax and enjoy
yourselves until you are sent for.
I like the sound of that. Why don't
we have ourselves a grand time?
（トロガイ）そいつは楽しみだ
たっぷり歓楽させてもらうとしようか
（シュガ）短槍は預からせてもらうぞ
We will look after your spear.
Chagum...
（二ノ妃(にのきさき)）チャグム…
Mother!
母君！
チャグム！
Chagum!
Mother!
母君！
Chagum...I always believed.
チャグム 母は信じていました
I always believed that you were
still alive somewhere out there...
そなたが どこかで生きていると
母は ずっと…
立派になりましたね
Look at how you have grown.
Yes, thanks to Balsa.
うん バルサのおかげだ
Yes, what became of that woman?
（二ノ妃）
そうじゃ あの女人はどうした？
She came back with me.
一緒に帰ってきた
She is probably somewhere
with Shuga in the palace.
今はシュガたちと
宮のどこかにいるはずだ
I see.
そうか…
（ガカイ）サグム殿下
ありがとうございました
Prince Sagum, thank you.
うあー いい湯じゃわい のう？
This bath hits the spot...
Doesn't it?
What's the matter?
You look awfully pensive over there.
どうした？ 神妙な顔しおって
It's nothing. It's finally starting
to hit home that it's really over.
別に
ただ 終わったんだなって
実感してたところです
What do you plan to do now?
お前
これから どうするつもりじゃ？
（バルサ）
さあ まだ何も考えられませんよ
I don't know. I still have no idea.
Set out on another journey?
また 旅に出るのか？
それも まだ何も…
I haven't given that
any thought either.
Actually, there's talk of
arranging a bride for Tanda.
実はタンダに嫁の話があってな
When I went to the health
springs over the winter...
冬の間に行っていた湯治場で―
古い知り合いに
しつこくせがまれてな
...an old acquaintance of mine
kept pestering me about it.
そこの娘が 隠居したじじいに
薬を煎じるタンダを見て―
She says her daughter...
...saw Tanda brewing medicine
for a retired old geezer there...
ほれちまったんだそうじゃ
...and fell head over heels for him.
顔は わしに似て
なかなかの美人でな
Like me, she's quite a looker.
She has a fine disposition too.
気立てもいい
（バルサ）いい話じゃないですか
They sound like a fine match.
（タンダ）はあ… まいったなあ
For heaven's sake...
I can't possibly eat all this food.
どう考えても
こんなに食べきれないよ
先に傷みそうなものから食べるか
I suppose I'll start with the food
that looks like it will go bad first.
（トロガイ）あほか！
Are you an idiot?
Don't be so stingy. Start with
whatever you want to eat!
しみったれたことせんと
食いたいものから食え
師匠 飲み過ぎじゃないですか？
Teacher, don't you think
you've had too much to drink?
（トロガイ）やかましい
Who asked you?
わしは宮中の酒を
飲み尽してやるつもりじゃ
I plan to drink every last drop
of liquor they have in the palace!
Hey! Bring me more sake!
おーい 酒を持ってこい！
Honestly...
まったく…
…にしても ふだんから
こんなものを食べていたんじゃ―
Still, it's no wonder that a simple
bowl of porridge seemed new to him...
１杯のかゆを新鮮に思うわけだ
なあ バルサ？
...if he was served
feasts like this every day.
Right, Balsa?
（バルサ）まあ… そうだね
I suppose so.
心配するなって
チャグムには すぐに会えるよ
Don't worry!
We'll see Chagum soon.
いくらなんも
あれっきりってはずはないだろ
That couldn't possibly have been
the last time we'd ever see him.
チャグムだって
お前に会いたいだろうしさ
Besides, I'm sure that Chagum
is just as eager to see you.
I guess you're right.
そうだね…
Look at me.
（帝）面を上げよ
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
Approach me.
（帝）もっと近(ちこ)う寄れ
No, closer.
もっとじゃ
よく戻った
It is good that you have returned.
Thank you.
はい
Shuga has informed me of
what transpired on your journey.
（帝）旅行きのこと
シュガより聞き及んだ
It must have been long and difficult.
つらく長い旅であったのう
だが 天子たるものにふさわしい―
Nevertheless, it was one
worthy of a child of heaven.
大儀であった
Truly a great deed.
（チャグム）それも
多くの者たちの力添えがあればこそ
It was only through the assistance of
a great many people that I succeeded.
特に バルサという者…
Especially that of Balsa, who--
Forget you ever met that woman!
（帝）その者のことは忘れよ！
To the common masses...
下々の者にとって そなたは
国の窮状を救った英雄なのだ
...you are the hero who saved
the country in her time of crisis.
国にとって
また そこに住まう者にとって―
For a country, as well as for
all those who reside in it...
１人の英雄を持つということは
誉れの極み
...having a hero is the
greatest possible honor.
いくら金を積んでも
引き換えることのかなわぬ―
One which no amount
of money can buy!
まさに天より授かりし宝物(ほうもつ)なのだ
You are a treasure
bestowed upon us by heaven!
聞けば そのカンバルの女人―
I am given to understand that this Kanbal
woman is a most capable individual...
損得を省みず 命を賭して
そなたを守り抜いた ひとかどの人物
...one who protected you with no
thought of reward or her own safety.
Surely she would have no
objections to you being our hero...
そなたが英雄となり―
この新ヨゴ皇国の行く末を
導くことに 何の異論があろう
...and guiding the
Shin-Yogo empire into the future.
チャグムよ―
Chagum...
Live as our hero.
英雄を生きよ
With Sagum now gone,
your role is now to live as a hero.
サグム亡き今―
英雄を生きることこそ
そなたの役目
For both you, who has made
an ally of the water spirit...
水の精霊を味方につけた そなたと―
...as well as for Shin-Yogo,
the road ahead is a bright one!
この新ヨゴ皇国の前途に
一点の曇りなし！
（チャグム）シュガ
バルサはどうしておる？
Shuga, what is Balsa doing?
She is resting in the
guest quarters, Your Highness.
（シュガ）
客間にて お休みになっております
I see...
（チャグム）そうか…
どうか分かってください
Please understand,
Your Highness.
あなた様は
ここに お戻りになられたときから―
The moment you returned here,
you became the crown prince.
すでに皇太子殿下となられたのです
Arrangements have been
made for them to receive...
彼らには あす 式典に先立ち―
相応以上の褒賞を贈るように
手配してあります
...a more than suitable reward
before the ceremony tomorrow.
（チャグム）バルサは きっと
こうなることが分かっていて―
Balsa must have known
that this would happen.
That is why she
told me about Jiguro.
ジグロの話をしてくれたのだな
How long are these people
going to keep us waiting?
（トロガイ）しかし
いつまで待たせる気だろうね
バルサ あれ
Balsa, is that...
Yeah.
They weren't kidding when they
said that the clothes make the man.
“馬子にも衣装”とは
よく言ったもんだ
師匠！
Teacher!
聞こえやしないよ
Relax, they can't hear me.
In light of your service to His Highness
the crown prince, child of heaven...
（シュガ）天子たる皇太子殿下に仕え
これを全うしたことに鑑み―
...His Majesty the mikado
shall now reward you!
帝より褒賞をつかわす
You there, step forward.
その者 前へ
次の者
Next.
Balsa, thank you.
バルサよ ありがとう
（シュガ）次の者
Next.
（トロガイ）あー 面倒くさいから
わしの分は お前がもらっておけ
It's too much trouble!
Go up there and fetch mine.
こんなのもらうより―
I'd rather talk to Chagum one more
time than receive something like this.
もう一度
チャグムと話がしたかったな
In that case, I'll take your
share off your hands later.
（トロガイ）なら お前の分は
あとで わしがもらってやるわい
You and your jokes...
（タンダ）また…
待て！
Halt! Commoners are not allowed
to pass through this gate.
ここは下々の民草が
通ってよい場所ではない
Go down the path to the right.
（モン）右の小道を行け
What's the meaning of this?
（トロガイ）どういうことだい？
（モン）その道こそ
お前たちにふさわしい
That path is more suitable
for the likes of you.
（タンダ）おい！ いくらなんでも…
Hey, I think you're
taking this a little too far.
Go.
（モン）行け
I suppose we should
do as they say for now.
ここは ひとまず
従ってやろうじゃないか
チャグム…
Chagum!
Balsa!
バルサ！
（チャグム）俺… 俺 やっぱり
皇太子になんか なりたくないよ
I...I don't want to be
the crown prince!
I want to keep traveling
with you forever!
ずっとバルサと旅していたいよ！
バルサと離れたくない
I don't want to leave you, Balsa!
（バルサ）
チャグム… 私と逃げるかい？
Chagum, do you want
to run away with me?
え？ ひと暴れしてやろうか？
Well? Would you like me
to cause a commotion?
（トロガイ）うむ…
暴れなくていいよ
You don't have to cause a commotion.
You can save it for some other child.
暴れるのは
別の子のためにとっておいて
あっ それって
タンダとバルサの子だったりしてね
And maybe that child
will be yours and Tanda's!
（トロガイ）ハッハッハッハッ…
こいつは最高だわい
That's a good one! Well said!
上出来！
You've learned to
speak your mind, I see!
お前 なかなか
言うようになったじゃないか
戻るよ
I'm going back now.
Right.
Balsa.
（チャグム）バルサ
俺のこと チャグムって呼んで
I want you to call me Chagum.
I want you to say,
"Goodbye, Chagum."
さようなら チャグムって言って
ああ… さようなら チャグム
Sure. Goodbye, Chagum.
Thank you, Balsa.
ありがとう バルサ
タンダ トロガイ師
Tanda, Torogai, goodbye.
さようなら
（タンダ）うん 師匠は
しばらく山小屋にいるみたいだ
Looks like Torogai will be
staying at the hut for a while.
She is, is she?
（トーヤ）そっかあ
ハァ… 俺も もう一度
チャグムと話したかったなあ
I wish I could've talked
to Chagum again too.
（サヤ）二度と会えないと
決まったわけじゃないんだから
Who's to say that you
won't see him again?
I guess, but...
（トーヤ）そうだけどさあ
（サヤ）
でも どうして バルサさん―
Still, I wonder why Balsa decided
to go back to Kanbal all of a sudden?
急にカンバルに
戻るだなんてことに？
Hey, that's right!
そうだよ チャグムが
８人目だったはずじゃなかったっけ？
I thought that Chagum was
supposed to be her eighth soul.
She said she was going to
settle down after that.
そしたら落ち着けるって
もう１人
どうしても バルサじゃないと―
There's one other person
that only Balsa can put to rest.
弔うことのできない人がいるのさ
ふーん 今度は
２年も待ちぼうけなきゃいいけど
Well, I just hope she doesn't keep you
waiting another two years this time.
If she does, I'll deal with it.
I'll still be here.
そうなったらそうなったで
そのときだ…
I swear, there's such a
thing as too much patience...
（トーヤ）
まったく 気が長いっていうか
（サヤ）ウフッ…
（タンダ）ん？
タンダ？
Tanda?
What's the matter, Tanda?
どうしたんだよ？ タンダ
（サヤ）あっ 雲…
A cloud!
I should have had some of Tanda's
wild vegetable stew before I left.
タンダの山菜鍋
食ってから来るんだったね
As I sat huddled and alone, holding back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like I was about to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were, at my side before I knew it.
It was none other than you who was there for me.
I keep wishing, "I want to be strong." I stumble and hurt myself again.
But because I have you to believe in, I can get back to my feet.
I simply want to tell my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs, again and again.
I call out to my precious loved one.
Is my voice reaching you?
In this world that always changes, human warmth never does.
I'm certain I sensed the presence of the one that I hold dear.
～♪